"It's kinda different from my drawings.
From:Nogame Musashi[mailto:nogame@fighter.com]
To:Chazawa Shinsuke
Subject:The character designs
Dear Chazawa,
Nogame
It's kinda different from my drawings.
It's kinda lacking the cute.
I'm kinda not okay with them.
（あおい）
“何か自分の絵と違います”
“何か可愛(かわい)さが足りない”
It's kinda lacking the cute.
I'm kinda not okay with them.
“何か納得がいきません　野亀(のがめ)”
Nogame."
（渡辺(わたなべ)）
それが原作者のメール
That's an email from the author.
The editor just received it.
さっき担当編集に
送られてきたらしい
（木下(きのした)）
う～ん
“なんか なんか”ってなんだよ
"Kinda" kinda doesn't tell us anything.
And I really liked these designs.
すごくいいと思ったんだけどな
I did too!
私も そう思いました
Not to mention the editor gave us the go-ahead.
それに担当編集者の方が
これで進めていいって
Sounds like he didn't get the
author's approval beforehand.
ちゃんと原作者に
確認 取ってなかったみたいだな
俺は このキャラデで
いきたいんだけど
I wanted to use these designs.
でも原作者からＮＧが出た以上
直さないわけにはいかない
But now that the author's vetoed them,
they have to be redone.
Either that,
もし直さないんだったら原作者を
納得させるだけの理由がいる
or we need to convince the author that we should stick with what we have.
Of course...
（木下）
だよね～
The keyframe animators have already started work up to episode 4.
あの 今 ４話まで原画作業に
入ってるんですけど　それは…
Will all that be—
Abort the mission.
（無線:渡辺）
攻撃中止だ
The hell? Why?!
（ミムジー）
うん？　なぜでありますか？
But the enemy's in our crosshairs!
（ロロ）
敵は目の前であります
Just back off!
（無線:渡辺）
いいから すぐに引き返せ
No way!
イヤであります
背後から攻撃が！
An attack from the rear?!
It's a retake rocket!
（ロロ）あれはリテーク弾
（爆発音）
（ロロ）うわ～
（ミムジー）落ちる～
We're going down!
Going down?!
（あおい）
落ちる？
まさか１話目からでありますか！
Wait, have we been screwed since the beginning?!
Flip the Table
線を整理したせいで
I guess the way you cleaned up the lines made them look too mature.
ちょっと大人っぽく
なっちゃったかもね
Maybe they should be a bit softer and girlier.
もう少し幼くしたほうが
いいんですかね？
I see
you!
Yeah... That might be it.
（木下）
なるほど そうかもしれないな
あっ ちょっと目を大きくして
位置を下げて
Eyes a bit bigger, a bit lower,
and their faces a bit more round... Could you do that?
あと少し輪郭を
柔らかくしてくれる？
（井口(いぐち)）
はい
Of course.
I'll ask the editor to start checking with the author more regularly.
（渡辺）
担当編集には もっとレス
早くしてもらえるよう頼んでおくよ
Thank you very much.
（あおい）
はい お願いします
And so that means we have to halt almost all work.
…ということですので
今 進めている作業は
止めてください
What do you mean, halt?
（佐藤(さとう)）
止めるというのは…
We stop doing every cut with the characters in them.
キャラクターに関係するところは
全部ストップ
（太郎(たろう)）
宮森(みやもり)！
Come on, Miyamori! We just started to gain momentum,
and now you're slamming on the brakes?
走りだした俺たちに
止まれってか！
原画のスケジュール
なくなるだろうが！
Then tell me: what should we do?
じゃあ 高梨(たかなし)さんだったら
どうします？
We should stop.
（太郎）止めるよ
（あおい）ですよね
Exactly.
Talk about being inflexible. Grats, newbie PM.
（平岡）
融通 利かねえな 新人デスクは
Why not let them continue and make the ADs fix it?
原画は進めておいて
後から作監作業で直せばいいだろ
That would be too much for the ADs to handle.
それだと
作監さんの負担が大きすぎます
If you stop them now, all keyframe work would need to be done in 3 weeks.
（平岡）
止めたら３週間以内で
原画を上げなきゃいけなくなる
You going the Boing-Boing route on us?
これも ぷるんぷるんするぞ
We can't do anything without the author's approval.
（あおい）
でも原作者のオーケーがないまま
進められません
教科書どおりじゃ
現場は乗り切れないだろ
This biz isn't always about
following every rule to a tee.
And we have new production assistants.
新人の制作も入ったんです
If we teach them to cut corners from the get-go, they'll make a habit—
最初に裏道を覚えたら
どんどん間違った方法に―
頼るようになるんじゃ…
（平岡）はいはい
Yeah, sure. Whatever you say, oh mighty PM.
了解ですよ デスク様
I'm getting some fresh air.
ちょっと出てきます
Which route should we take?
あの…
（安藤(あんどう)）
私たち どっちのルートを
通ればいいんですか？
Just follow me and you'll be right as rain.
俺が歩く後ろをついてくればいい
First, load the storyboards to the Xerox—
まずはコンテ原版をソーターに…
安藤さんと佐藤さんは
正しいルートね
We're doing things the proper way.
Okay.
（安藤･佐藤）はい
（太郎）…ってスルー！
Hey!
（遠藤(えんどう)）
本当に止めんのかよ
Are you really stopping us?
I'm sorry...
すみません
俺 ２話のレイアウト作監
入れちゃったよ
I've already started layout AD work on episode 2.
すいません 急いで直しますんで
Sorry! I'll get them fixed ASAP.
It's not your fault, Iguchi-san.
（遠藤）
あ～ いや
井口さんのせいじゃないけどさ
（木下）
はあ～ せっかくコンテも
調子に乗ってたのにな～
Storyboard work was going so well too.
（みどり）
あっ 「ぷるんぷるん天国」の
再来ですかね？
So is this going to end up like Boing-Boing Paradise?
（木下）やめて～
（みどり）あっ そっか
No! Anything but that!
Oh, right.
That wasn't because of an issue with the original's author.
あれは原作者との
トラブルじゃなくて
監督のコンテとコンテチェックが
遅れたのをきっかけに
That was because you delayed
storyboards and all those checks.
Which backed up the whole schedule, right?
スケジュールが
大崩壊したんでしたね
That's pretty much it,
but I'd rather you not remind me!
（木下）
おおむね正しいけど
確認しないで～
すいません
Sorry! I have this habit of always trying to confirm the facts!
事実関係ハッキリさせる
癖がついちゃって
Here's the author's feedback.
（渡辺）
原作者からのレスが来た
"Cute and childish aren't the same.
（あおい）
“かわいいと幼いは
なんか違います”
Redraw, please.
“描き直してください　野亀”
Nogame."
Anything else?
（木下）他に意見は？
（渡辺）それだけだ
No, that's it.
Okay, I got it.
分かりました
等身 高くして調整してみます
I'll try adjusting the proportions.
Another response from the author.
（渡辺）
原作者からのレスが来た
"It's getting worse and worse.
“どんどん悪くなります”
Does she actually think these drawings are good?
“この人は自分の描いたものを
いいと思ってるんでしょうか？”
“キャラデ この方で
大丈夫ですか？　野亀”
Can we really rely on her as character designer?
Nogame."
He's basically saying we should replace her, right?
（葛城(かつらぎ)）
これって暗に降ろせって
言ってるようなもんだよね
We can't just read any of that to Iguchi-san.
そのまま井口さんには
伝えられないな～
What should we do?
（あおい）
どうすればいいんでしょう？
I'll call the editor and ask how exactly we should fix it.
担当編集 つかまえて
直しの方向性 聞いてみる
Funny thing is, the author's told you all you need to know. Figure out the rest yourself!
（茶沢(ちゃざわ)）
いや 変な話
先生のメールが全てなんで
そこから くみ取ってください
Isn't that your job?
そういうの そちらの
仕事なんじゃないですか～？
いや あのメールだけでは
直しの方向が分かりません
The instructions in his responses are just too vague.
Do we have to spoon-feed you every little thing?
（茶沢）
こっちが全部 指示しなきゃ
いけないんですかね～
Sorry for being a nuisance, but we need the author's—
お手数かけて
申し訳ありませんが
先生に…
（茶沢）だから無理なんで
Not a chance!
Funny thing is, he has a deadline coming up!
（茶沢）
変な話
先生 今 締め切り前なんで―
（通話が切れた音）
あの！
But—
He hung up?
えっ えっ…
電話 切られちゃった？
Funny thing is, I don't get this guy.
全然 訳分かんねえよ 変な話
Funny thing is, now you're talking like he does.
口癖うつっちゃったね 変な話
I'm sorry...
すみません 私の中でも
どう直していいか見えなくて
I can't seem to figure out how I'm supposed to draw them.
No, this is our fault.
いや こっちこそ
本当に申し訳ない
Sorry for all this...
何度もごめんね
If only we could meet with the author...
せめて原作者に
会わせてもらえればな
We'll have to cope by ourselves for now.
とにかく今は
こっちでやるしかない
Let's start from square one. Reconsider everything.
もう一度 基本に戻って
最初から検証してみよう
Got it.
分かりました
I'll try to figure out what exactly the author is so particular about
原作者の方が
こだわってる部分を探って
and make my designs match the originals better.
もう少し原作の線を拾った
キャラデにしてみます
Which path's the cutest?
かわいい道はどっち？
This way, maybe.
（ロロ）
こっちかな？
Who are you?
（ミムジー）
あなたは？
I am the author!
（原作者）
予は原作者であるぞ
I have a bonus quiz for you!
さ～て ここでボーナスクイ～ズ！
かわいいのは どっちかな？
Which one of these is cute?
Um...
う～んと
Hm, let's see...
（原作者）チチチ…
（ロロ）どっちかな？
This one!
（ミムジー）こっち
（ロロ）こっちだよ
No, this!
ブ～！　どっちもハズレ！
Both wrong!
（ミムジー）やっぱり落ちる～！
（ロロ）うわ～
Oh no, not again!
Miyamori, what's happening with the character designs?
（太郎）
みゃーもり キャラデどうなった？
We still haven't got the author's approval.
（あおい）
まだ原作者のオーケー出ません
（太郎）
マジか！　オンエアまで
あと３か月じゃないか
For reals?! We've only got three months until airtime!
We're getting further and further behind schedule.
なんか どんどんスケジュール
なくなっていきますね
Will everything be okay?
大丈夫なんでしょうか？
（太郎）
大丈夫ではない
No, not at all!
But it's up to us in production to make things all better!
しかし そこを
大丈夫にするのが制作だ
Wow!
すご～い
Would you be able to fix this situation, Takanashi-san?
高梨さんだったら この状況
大丈夫にできるんですか？
（あおい）できません
（太郎）あっ…
He wouldn't.
Really?
（佐藤）そうなんですか？
（太郎）ごめんなさい！
So sorry!
3rd Girls' Fighter Wing
Oi-chan?
（絵麻(えま)）おいちゃん？
（あおい）うん？
（絵麻）井口さん 捜してる？
（あおい）うん
Are you looking for Iguchi-san?
Yeah.
I think she's out there.
（絵麻）
多分 あそこだと思う
Iguchi-san!
井口さん
Are you okay?
大丈夫ですか？
えっ？
あっ ごめん ぼ～っとしてた
Sorry, I was just spacing out.
よく ここ分かったね
あっ 絵麻っちに聞いた？
How did you know I was here?
Oh, Emacchi told you?
Yes.
あっ はい　すみません
Sorry for putting all of this on you, Iguchi-san.
井口さんばかりに
負担をかけてしまって
いや～
こっちこそ待たせてごめんね
Nah. I'm the one stalling everything.
I have no idea how I'm supposed to fix them up.
もう どう直していいか
分かんなくなっちゃって
But I'll figure it out!
（井口）でも頑張る
（あおい）あっ
Ogasawara-san recommended me, after all.
（井口）
せっかく
小笠原(おがさわら)さんが推薦してくれたんだし
This is my big chance after
doing keyframes for six years.
原画６年やって
初めて来たチャンスだし
Not to mention I really got to like Aria, Catherine, and all the characters.
それに ありあや
キャサリンたちのこと
すごく好きになったし
Um... I...
あの！　えっと その…
It's my first project being PM, so I'm sorry if I screw up!
私も初めてのデスクで
至らないことだらけですけど…
（ニャ次郎(じろう)）ニャ～
（あおい）あっ…
うん… 頑張るニャ
I'll do my-ow best.
フッ　うん 頑張るニャ
Me-ow too.
MiG-23ML Flogger
Kfir C2
JA37 Viggen
F-4D Phantom
F-1
E-2A Hawkeye
MC-130E Combat Talon
F-22 Raptor
F-35A Lightning
B-1B Lancer
3rd Girls' Fighter Wing Concept Art
Name                                                   Type       Note
Midway Pillar
Setting   A giant pillar footed on the Midway island. Its foot is geometrically weird
Base Runway                                       Setting   Cathy's rescue
Chofu Base - Total                               Setting
Chofu Base - Hangar                           Setting
Chofu Base - Runway                          Setting   Aria's training
Chofu Base - Command Room           Setting   Cathy joins the 3rd Wing. There's a wired phone.
Chofu Base - Aria and Cathy's Room  Setting
Chofu Base - Shower Room
Setting
Chofu Base - In front of the Hangar
Didn't we stop work?
（佐藤）
作業 止めたんじゃないんですか？
Chofu Base - In front of the Hangar
We did.
（あおい）
うん　でも３Ｄや美術は
キャラクターができなくても
But you don't need the characters for the backgrounds and the CG, do you?
進められるでしょ？
You're right!
あ～ なるほど
The studio is like a living creature.
現場は生き物っていうからね
いつも何かが起きる
Always something going on.
So we've got to do what we can now.
だから 今できることを
やっておかないとね
It's bringing back all those memories of how you panicked when you were running your first episode.
いや 今でこそ
こんなことが言えるけどな～
こいつ 初めて
１話まるまる担当した時
めっちゃパニクってたんだよな
That was because you hid the mess about the keyframes!
あれは高梨さんが原画 隠したから
（太郎）
隠してないよ
上がらなかったの黙ってただけだよ
I wasn't hiding that.
I just happened to not tell anyone they weren't getting done.
だが そこから俺は
フェニックスのように立ち直った
And then I was reborn from my ashes like a phoenix!
…で 遠藤さんが降りる降りない
って話になったんですよね
You almost made Endou-san quit doing the episode.
And Idepon Miyamori saved me!
（太郎）
イデポン宮森には
お世話になりました
You're welcome.
いえいえ どういたしまして
Idepon? What does that mean?
イデポンってなんですか？
A great divine who far transcended humankind!
（あおい）
人間を超越した万物の意思
So that's why Takanashi-san stands no chance against Miyamori-senpai!
（安藤）
あ～ だから高梨さんは
宮森先輩に勝てないんですね
That totally makes sense!
（安藤）納得です
（太郎）するなよ！
No, it doesn't!
I agree. It doesn't.
（佐藤）
よく分かりません
After the CG stuff, we'll meet with the background artists.
（あおい）
３Ｄの後は美術さんとの打ち合わせ
Some props and pasting materials are done too, so please check them.
それからプロップと貼り込み素材が
上がってるんで
チェックをお願いします
（木下）
なんだよ 張り切ってんな～
こんな非常事態に
You're pretty fired up despite this mess we're in.
No, because of it!
（あおい）だからです
（木下）えっ？
You did the storyboards faster than I'd thought possible.
監督のコンテが信じられないほど
早く上がって 現場も動きだして
Work finally started and everyone was starting to get in the mood!
みんな やる気になってたところ
だったんですから
I want to maintain that momentum!
そのノリと勢いを
キープしたいです
"Faster than I'd thought possible" is a compliment, right?
（木下）
信じられないほど早く上がったは
褒め言葉だよね？
You're not making fun of me?
（木下）嫌みじゃないよね？
（あおい）もちろんです
Of course not!
I work better with positive reinforcement, so please don't be too harsh with me!
俺 褒められて伸びるタイプだから
あんまり怒らないでね
I know.
分かってます　褒めすぎると
調子に乗ることも含めて
I also know what happens when you're complimented too much.
テヘッ
Tee-hee.
（下柳(しもやなぎ)）
結構 実物に近い動きができたと
思うんですけど どうでしょう？
I think we managed to make them move like the real thing.
What do you think?
う～ん もうちょっと挙動に
スピード感がほしいかな～
I'd like them to look a bit less stiff.
I want to emphasize the visuals in 3rd Wing.
「サンジョ」は視覚的な快感を
優先させたいんだよね
Sure, but it'll look less realistic.
（下柳）
そうすると
リアルじゃなくなりますよ
そこはバランスかな
We've gotta find the right balance.
カッコよくウソをつく
ってのを目指したいんだよね
Let's exaggerate things a bit to really make it look cool.
Make them move faster, more wildly.
もっと生き生き大胆に
動かしてほしいかな
Think of them as the machine versions of their pilots.
パイロットのイメージに
かぶるように擬人化してさ
ありあが乗るＦ１はクールで力強く
Aria's F-1 should be cool and strong.
Catherine's Phantom would be cheerful and energetic.
キャサリンのファントムなら
元気に明るく　どうかな？
How's that sound?
I got it. We'll redo the motions with that in mind.
分かりました
その線で
モーションつけ直してみます
The planes are the leads of this show.
この作品は飛行機が主役だから
The planes are the leads?
飛行機が主役…
These stratocumulus form around 2,000 meters in altitude.
（渥美(あつみ)）
高度2,000メートルに出来る
層積雲です
Altitude?
高度？
空の高さによって
出来る雲が違うんです
The elevation determines the types of clouds that form.
I see!
そうなんですか
These clouds tell tales about how the characters feel.
この雲は
キャラクターの心情を語る雲です
It's sort of sad in a way.
なんか ちょっと
寂しい感じするよね
Yeah.
（渥美）
はい
They wanted to fly towards the future, but it still feels so hollow.
未来を信じて飛んだはずなのに
どこかむなしい
That's what I wanted to express here.
そんな気持ちを
表現してみました
In episode 1, I can imagine these clouds under the returning formation of the 3rd Wing.
１話の帰還シーン
サンジョの編隊の下に
こういう雲が走ってるといいな～
These clouds are too low for that.
それには雲の高度が低すぎます
Then we'll just lower the planes.
じゃあ 飛行機が高度を下げるよ
Of course it won't be a realistic altitude,
（木下）
もちろんウソの高度には
なっちゃうけどさ
but let's use some artistic license to carry the mood.
そこは心情を優先させたいな
I'd love a scene with nothing but the skyline and some music.
音楽のっけて ず～っと空と雲を
映すって絵も作りたいな～
Without any characters or planes?
（渥美）
飛行機もキャラもなしでですか？
Yeah. Art is basically the lead of this show.
この作品は美術が主役だからね
I get it.
分かりました
I'll draw you skies and clouds worthy of being the leads.
主役になりうる空と雲を
描かせていただきます
You're telling everyone the same thing, aren't you?
（あおい）
監督 みんなに同じこと
言ってますよね
（木下）えっ？
（あおい）主役 多くないですか？
Aren't there a few too many leads?
（木下）
それ みんなに言ってるっけ？
Have I been telling everyone that?
Yeah. You said it to the filming staff and the color designer too.
はい 撮影さんや色彩設計さんにも
You're like a playboy trying to juggle all the girls.
何股もかけてる男の人みたいです
いえいえ 私は本気で言ってますよ
No, I'm not. And I meant what I said.
And I've personally never juggled any number of ladies, by the way.
ちなみに私生活では
何股もかけたことはありません
You know, 3rd Wing isn't all about the flashy stuff.
「サンジョ」はさ
ただドンパチやるんじゃなくて
絵に心象が
反映されるようにしたいんだよね
I want every scene to embody specific emotions.
絵に心象が…
Such as?
For example...
（木下）
例えば―
When it's winter,
冬にコンテが上がらなくて
you're having trouble with the storyboards,
and you go out stargazing and see Orion.
外の階段から夜空を見上げた時の
オリオン座
作品がたたかれて
泣きそうになった帰り道
When you're on the verge of tears because your show is getting bashed,
and on the way home you glance up and see the red sunset.
ふと見上げた赤い夕日
The indirect lighting cast in your living room,
which feels way too big after your wife left for good.
奥さんが実家に帰った後の
１人には広すぎる―
リビングの間接照明
Then as they reject your—
それから納品を拒否られた…
よく分かりました
全部 悲しいですけどね
I get it.
They're all pretty sad.
アハハ…
I see
you!
I can't see it.
見えない
Sorry... I know it's been over ten days now.
（井口）
ごめん
10日以上も引っ張っちゃって
It's fine.
あっ いえ…
I just keep returning to my previous drawings. I'm not even sure what works anymore.
（井口）
どうしても前の絵に
引っ張られちゃって
何が正しいか
分からなくなっちゃった
I'm really sorry.
ホントにごめんね
Everything's stalled without the character designs.
キャラデ上がんないと
作業 進められないのに
No, it's our fault.
いえ こちらこそ すいません
One, two, three, four...
１ ２ ３ ４ ５ ６ ７ ８
five, six, seven, eight...
Eins, zwei, drei, vier...
アイン ツヴァイ
ドライ フィーア
フュンフ ゼクス
ズィーベン アハト
fünf, sechs, sieben, acht...
Yī, èr, sān, sì...
イー リャン サン スー
ウー ロー チー パー
Wǔ, liù, qī, bā...
（絵麻）ハッ あ～！
（井口）あっ ごめん
Sorry.
What kind of exercise is that?
それ なんの体操？
あっ 肩に効く
エンゼル体操っていうんですけど
It's good for the shoulders. It's called the Angel.
エンゼル？
Angel?
It's supposed to make you feel like an angel afterwards.
終わった後
天使のような気持ちになるって
It used to be kind of popular.
一部で はやってて
へえ～
（井口･絵麻）
ひー ふー みー よー
いつ むー なな やー
One, two, three, four...
Five, six, seven, eight...
ウーノ ドゥーエ トレ クワットロ
チンクェ セーイ セッテ オット
Uno, due, tre, quattro...
Cinque, sei, sette, otto...
I really do feel a bit lighter.
うん ちょっと肩 軽くなった
Um...
（絵麻）あの…
（井口）うん？
Is there anything I can do to help?
私に何かできることありますか？
I'm fine. Sorry if I made you worry.
大丈夫 心配かけてごめん
I like them.
（絵麻）私 好きです
（井口）えっ？
I really like how full of life your designs are.
井口さんの絵
元気があって とても好きです
I'm really looking forward to making them move.
その絵を動かすの
すごく楽しみです
I'm looking forward to it too.
私も楽しみ
どれだけ作品やってても
No matter how many shows you do,
it never gets old seeing your drawings come to life.
自分が描いた絵が動いてるのを
見る時の感動は
なんともいえないよね
And they'll be my character designs this time.
ましてや 今回はキャラデだもん
I wanna see Aria and her friends talk and laugh as soon as possible.
ありあたちが しゃべったり
笑ったりするとこを早く見たい
I really do!
すごく見たい
You have not been providing sufficient support.
（小笠原）
サポートが足りないと思うのです
This is the first time Iguchi-san has handled character designs.
井口さんは今回 初めて
キャラクターデザインを
担当しています
Despite this, you have simply thrown
everything at her, abandoning her to her struggle.
なのに あなた方は井口さんを
ずっと放りっぱなしでは
ありませんか
The author wouldn't tell us how to fix the designs, though.
（木下）えっ
（渡辺）いや～
原作者が どう直していいか
言ってくれなくて
Even if the author has been less than forthcoming,
原作者が
何も言ってくれないからといって
it speaks of laziness on your part to leave everything to Iguchi-san.
その全てを
井口さんに丸投げするのは
仕事を放棄しているのと同じです
It makes little sense.
それでは あんまりではないですか
You assigned her that job, so it is your responsibility in turn to consult with and advise her.
井口さんを抜てきしたのなら
ちゃんと相談に乗ったり
アドバイスしてあげてください
You're right.
確かに そのとおり
申し訳ない
We're so sorry.
Try to facilitate an environment in which she can concentrate on her work without feeling burdened.
（小笠原）
井口さんに負担のかからない―
作業に集中できる環境を
作ってあげてください
And...
そして 最後まで しっかり
Please support her to the very end.
井口さんを
支えてさしあげてください
Okay.
（木下･渡辺）
はい
Then let's go invite her for lunch to take her mind off work!
じゃあ 井口さん誘って
気分転換に飯でも
And maybe go for a pint—
飲みに行っちゃう？
（小笠原）
あなた方の仕事は
それではありません
That is not your job.
You must determine the author's true wishes and help Iguchi-san figure out how to adjust the designs.
（小笠原）
原作者の意向を解釈して
もっと井口さんと一緒に
直しの方向性を考えてください
Okay.
（木下･渡辺）はい
（小笠原）お酒を飲めば
Do not assume that alcohol is a valid form of stress relief for everyone.
誰でも気分転換になると
思わないでください
There are people who do not find it relaxing at all.
そういうことが
苦手な方もいるのをお忘れなく
Okay.
（木下･渡辺）
はい
Miyamori-san, would you mind coming with me?
宮森さん ちょっと
つきあっていただけます？
You too, Yasuhara-san.
（小笠原）そうね 安原(やすはら)さんも
（絵麻）ああっ！
So where are we headed?
（井口）
私 どこに
連れていかれるんですか？
My oasis.
わたくしのオアシスよ
Your oasis?
小笠原さんのオアシス…
（絵麻･あおい）
ウフフ…
（井口）
うわ～ 私 絶対 似合わないです
There's no way that'd look good on me!
I do not know exactly what you are imagining, but you are definitely off the mark.
井口さんが何を考えているか
知りませんが―
違います
（井口）ホッ
This is your oasis?
ここが小笠原さんのオアシス？
That is correct.
そうです
ふんっ
Play ball!
（機械音声）
プレーボール
ふんっ
えいっ
せいっ
Strike!
（機械音声）
ストライ～ク
ストライ～ク！
ストスト… ストライ～ク！
（絵麻）うわ～
（井口）何者？
Is she human?
This could be an anime!
なんかアニメになりそう
Gothloli Koshien
Gothloli Koshien!
（ナレーション）
「女ゴスロリ甲子園」
Gothloli Koshien
Koshien
Stadium
Hamburger Lunch
with
Rice
Hamburger Lunch
with
Rice
Cattle Dive
少しは気晴らしになりました？
Did that help relieve some stress?
Yes! I saw something as rare as a living unicorn!
はい！
めったに見られないものが見れて
Did you use to play softball, Ogasawara-san?
小笠原さん ソフトボールとか
やってたんですか？
No, I used to be in the Go club.
（小笠原）いえ 私は囲碁部でした
（井口）囲碁？
Go?
Black and white. True to your gothloli ima—
うわ～ 白くて黒くて
さすがゴスロリさ… あっ
I am quite aware people call me that.
そう呼ばれていることは
知っています
Have you always dressed this way?
前から
そのファッションだったんですか？
（小笠原）
昔はいつも
Ｔシャツにジーパンでした
I used to wear T-shirts and jeans.
You did?
（井口）
小笠原さんが？
I'd like to see that.
見てみたかった
When'd you start dressing like this?
じゃあ いつから その姿に？
Characters
The Sisters (Color Concept)
1: Ash
2: Or
3: Verde
4: Brou
5: Rouge (MC)
6: Rosa
7: Blanc
Me? Character designs?
（小笠原）
私にキャラクターデザインを？
The show's based on a video game.
Director
（プロデューサー）
ゲーム原作の作品なんだけど
Wanna try?
（監督）
やってみる？
Sure! I'd love to do it!
はい ぜひ
やらせていただきたいです
It's not exactly bad, but...
（プロデューサー）
う～ん 悪くはないけどな～
Director
Try another style.
別のパターンも見せて
Okay.
あっ はい
（プロデューサー）
う～ん 悪くはないんだけどね～
It's still not bad...
Director
It's a bit different from what I had in mind.
微妙にイメージと違うな
また別のパターンで
Try another style again.
Okay...
あっ はい
Director
（監督）
ちょっと地味に…
This is too bland.
Too pointy!
（プロデューサー）
いや～ とんがりすぎでしょ
この目はないよね～
It feels unfinished.
These eyes won't do.
That's not it.
（監督）いや そうじゃなくてだね
（プロデューサー）逆に言うとね
On the other hand...
Director
（小笠原）
追い込まれても
勝負をひっくり返されても
I thought I could stand my ground even if I was cornered,
even if everything was against me....
へこたれないほうだと
思ってましたが…
Director
最初のが一番よかったよね
The first one was the best.
Right?
（プロデューサー）
だよね～
Asagaya
That was when I realized that I cannot simply accept everything with an obedient nod.
（小笠原）
その時 理解したのです
全てに“はいはい”と
うなずいていてはいけないのだと
Asagaya
Every artist has a sensitive and vulnerable heart.
クリエーターは誰しも
繊細で傷つきやすい心を持っている
Yet we are constantly criticized, rejected, and faced with demands.
しかし絶えず批評 ダメ出し
注文をつけられる
So in order to protect myself,
だから自分を守るために…
I donned this armor.
わたくしは鎧(よろい)をまとったのです
So that's your battle gear?
それは武装だったんですね
It definitely seems more powerful than a T-shirt.
確かにＴシャツよりは
攻撃力 高そう
But why—
えっと… でも なぜ…
Because the heroine I was drawing then dressed as such.
その時 描いていたヒロインが
着ていたからです
It's made me stronger.
それから私は強くなりました
It's reassuring to know that even you've had trouble with stuff before.
安心しました
小笠原さんも
つらい時期があったんですね
Everyone does.
誰にだってあります
There is no profession that is free from challenges.
つらい時期のない職業なんて
ありません
The question is only how well you can turn humiliation into progression.
ですから後は屈辱をバネに
どれだけ自分が頑張れるかです
"It's kinda different from my drawings.
“何か自分の絵と違います
何か可愛さが足りない”
It's kinda lacking the cute."
I thought about it, and I guess we might've been too focused on making it moe.
考えたんだけど ちょっと萌(も)えを
意識しすぎたかなって
You're correct.
そうですね
Girlishness might not be the key here.
女の子っぽくする方向では
ないのかもしれません
I believe the author's conception of cute is not based on that.
原作者の考えるかわいさとは
中性的なかわいさなのでは
ないでしょうか
I see! Now I get why Aria is cute and all!
あっ 確かに
ありあのかわいく見える謎が
解けた気がします！
Okay! Let's try that next!
（渡辺）
よし その線でいってみるか
Okay!
（井口）
はい！
Good morn—
おはようございま…
（あおい）えっ？
（井口）おはよう
Morning!
Iguchi-san... Are you cosplaying as Aria from episode 3?
井口さん それは もしかしたら
３話のありあのコスプレ？
I looked for a halberd too, but couldn't find one.
（井口）
なぎなたは探したんだけど
なくってさ～
Is that really what you should be focusing on?
頑張るとこ そこですか？
井口さん
Yeah! I'll arm myself too and storm into battle!
うん 私も武装して頑張ってみる
There's more to come, too.
これが全てじゃないけどね
This is Aria...
（井口）
ありあになった
It's closer to the original art, yet it's also easy to animate.
原作の絵に寄せつつ
動かしやすい絵になってる
The earlier designs were nice,
but this really captures the spirit of the original.
前のもよかったけど
こっちのほうが
確かに原作の雰囲気が出てるな
It's like you added some cool to the cute!
かわいさに
りりしさが足された気がします
Aria's willpower shines through!
ありあの意志の強さっていうか
If this doesn't work, I'll go and convince the author myself.
これでダメだったら
原作者 説得するから
Thank you!
お願いします！
Home run.
ホームランです
I'll ask for an appointment from the editor.
じゃあ早速 担当編集にアポを取る
I'll get an answer today, whatever it takes.
絶対 今日中に
返事もらってくるからな
はい
Great!
Um, funny thing is, I'm kinda in the middle of—
いや～ 変な話
今 取り込み中なんで…
そこをなんとか
This is urgent!
I'm busy, so some other time.
（茶沢）忙しいんで また改めて
（スイングの音）
Funny thing is, I know where he is.
変な話 ヤツの所在は分かった
音から察するに…
Judging from the sound...
It's near the publisher's headquarters!
恐らく出版社の近くの…
う～ん ナイスショット！　うん？
Nice shot!
Wait, what? How did you know?!
なんだなんだ どうしてここが？
F-Funny thing is, I'm work—
あっ いや変な話 仕事中…
現場は もう１か月も
止まってるんです！
Keyframes have been stalled for a month now!
Get feedback from the author right away!
すぐに原作者の
確認を取ってください！　変な話
Funny thing.
Email from the author!
原作者さんからのメールです！
"It's gotten much better.
“よくなったと思います
これでいいです　野亀”
This will do.
Nogame."
Aria Fourseasons
Rough Draft
Musani, Andou speaking.
Ah, Hirao-san! Your circle had a booth at the summer festival, right?
I got a volume myself!
Next time on Shirobako: "Where am I..."
Where am I...
（安藤）
はい ムサニの安藤です
あっ 平尾(ひらお)さん　夏フェス
サークル参加されてましたよね
１冊 買いました
次回
「ＳＨＩＲＯＢＡＫＯ(シロバコ)」